We pick up with two dots on the bottom of מ"ט עמוד
א. Mem Tet Amud Aleph. כמעשהו בחול K'ma'aseihu b'chol and we are
wrapping up the discussion
of the ניסוך המים.
Nisuch
Hamayim. So this פרק perek has really been one where we deal
with the collection of the מצוות mitzvos that apply on סוכות Sukkos
where we had לולב Lulav which we obviously knew but then we
elaborated on ones that are מקדש Mikdash related. We had ערבה, Arava,
obviously an element of ערבה Arava outside of the מקדש Mikdash and
then we had ניסוך המים Nisuch Hamayim which has been a very
dominant מקדש Mikdash ritual which is going to continue in the next
פרק perek with the שמחת בית השואבה Simchas Beis Hashoeva that was
done the preceding night. So here we are though wrapping up the
aspects of the ניסוך המים Nisuch Hamayim and it says that they
would do the same thing they would do on the weekday they
would do on שבת Shabbos except on the weekday they would draw
the water from the wellspring on ערב שבת erev Shabbos and they
would fill it up and put it in a barrel or they
would take it from that barrel on שבת. Shabbos. Okay. The ניסוך
המים Nisuch Hamayim was always night? I'm sorry? Was it night? The
ניסוך המים Nisuch Hamayim was in the day with the תמיד של
שחר Tamid shel Shachar together with the wine libations of the תמיד
של שחר Tamid shel Shachar but the
שמחת בית השואבה Simchas Beis Hashoeva started the night before and was
like partying through the night, this is what we're going to read
in the next פרק, perek, and then it led through the morning
through the was accompanied the drawing of the water and then come
taking the water into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and doing the
pouring of the water. So it was a previous night celebration that
you know led into the next day's ניסוך המים. Nisuch Hamayim.
So it's done at night?
No, this wasn't done at night, it was just the celebration in
anticipation of it and so on. The עבודה avoda was done in
the day. The pouring is, yeah. The pouring was done with the
תמיד של שחר, Tamid shel Shachar, the pouring of the water with
the תמיד של שחר. Tamid shel Shachar. Right. Okay, so now the
last משנה Mishna says the following.
Let's take a look. Okay, כמעשהו בחול. K'ma'aseihu b'chol.
So they would do the same thing on the weekday as they
would do on שבת Shabbos or they would do on the same
thing on שבת Shabbos they would do on the weekday except as
I said they filled up this barrel and the gold barrel the
משנה Mishna says but it says אינה מקודשת, aina mekudeshes, a non-sanctified
gold barrel, the water would sit in it until they could draw
it from it the next morning but it was already in the
מקדש. Mikdash. So ואמאי v'amai why says the גמרא Gemara ונעביד במקודשת?
v'na'avid b'mekudeshes? Why not just have a sanctified gold barrel? Why specifically
have a non-sanctified one that it would be sitting in? So אמר
זעירי Amar Ze'iri קסבר Kasavar because this תנא Tanna is of the
opinion אין שיעור למים, ain shiur l'mayim, there's actually no exact amount
of water. Yes we do three לוג log but it doesn't have
to be precisely three לוג, log, וכלי שרת מקדשין שלא מדעת. v'klei
shares mekadshin shelo m'da'as. And sanctified vessels sanctify even without intent. What
does this mean and what are these two factors? So it means
the following. The normal principle is that things as opposed to like
livestock which have to be slaughtered to be sanctified to reach their
highest level of sanctity, קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, something like let's say
inanimate like a מנחה Mincha is sanctified when it's put into a
vessel, when it's put into a כלי שרת, klei shares, one of
the Temple holy vessels. Now,
is anything and what one of the significances of that קדושת הגוף
kedushas haguf as opposed to just sanctifying the flower verbally is that
once it gets that it's at the full level of a קרבן
Korban which means that if it stays overnight it's לינה, lina, right
then it's like לא תלין, lo salin, you know letting your קרבן
Korban stay overnight and then it becomes invalid. If it's taken out
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash it's invalid. So that is relevant
once it gets קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf where for inanimate things basically
means once it's put in a כלי שרת. klei shares. So the
גמרא's Gemara point is if the barrel was sanctified and you filled
up the water it would become sanctified as קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf,
intrinsic sanctity you know at its essence and therefore it would become
invalid by the next morning when you actually needed to use it.
Okay, so just say that. Why do you have to say שלא
מדעת? shelo m'da'as? Why do you have to say that there's no
minimum amount? Well שלא מדעת shelo m'da'as is clear why it has
to say because maybe you could say look maybe the כלי שרת
klei shares should only sanctify when I want it to sanctify the
thing that's in it. If I intentionally say I'm drawing this water
from the well from the spring yet but it should not be
sanctified because I'm going to need it tomorrow morning, so maybe it
isn't, maybe if I
designated that way it won't have that effect. No, the very fact
of it being in a כלי שרת klei shares imparts that sanctity
even if it was not your and even if your intent was
the opposite of that. That's שלא מדעת. shelo m'da'as. So you'll be
stuck, the water will be sanctified it will become invalid Friday night
you know over Friday night. Well then what's the point of saying
אין לו שיעור? ain lo shiur? Because you could say another point.
Okay, fine, we're not going to go with your intent. We're going
to go with the objective reality. But if the objective reality is
that the water needed for the libation is three לוג log and
in this here כלי שרת klei shares you can tell it's a
כלי שרת klei shares because it's so fancy and everything, in this
here כלי שרת klei shares you have five לוג log of water,
so then the objective reality is that it's not the water that
is you know ready to be used in the ritual, meaning yes
you could get the water out of it, it's not that it's
you know it's too much, it's not that it's not. Enough, but
nevertheless the whole idea of a כלי שרת Kli Shares and the
whole idea of the קדושת הגוף Kedushas Haguf is it basically says
like, this is about to be offered up, you know, this is
in the state that it's not just been sanctified verbally, it's really
in that state of about to be offered up. So if there's
too much water in here and you say, okay fine, your intent
doesn't matter, it'll work שלא מדעת, shelo midaas, but it shouldn't be
sanctified because the objective reality shows that it's not ready yet, that
this isn't exactly what you need. This is five לוג, Log, it's
not three לוג. Log. So that's why the גמרא Gemara says no,
also אין לו שיעור. ein lo shiur. Although we use three לוג,
Log, technically it could be any amount. And therefore, the objective reality
is once the water is in here, it automatically becomes sanctified no
matter how much there is, no matter if you don't want it
to be sanctified. And therefore we can't do it the day before
because it'll become invalid by the next morning. Okay, so now let's
see how the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, ואי מייתי בכלי מקודש v'ee
maysee b'kli mekudash and therefore if you bring it in a sanctified
barrel and you have it stay over the whole night, יפסלוהו בלינה
yipsulu linu become invalid by לינה. lina. Okay. Now by the way,
תוספות Tosafos asks a very good question, there's a big תוספות Tosafos
here. Part of the תוספות Tosafos deals with this issue of like,
well, the basic תוספות Tosafos deals with the following question. Why do
you have to say it's פסול בלינה? passul b'lina? As soon as
I go out to draw the water from the from the wellspring,
I'm outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So if that was a
sanctified vessel and it all happened automatically, then it's immediately פסול ביוצא
passul b'yotzei because it's outside of the temple environs. So תוספות Tosafos
alright there's an obvious answer to that, which something cannot become sanctified
out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, right? You can't say, ah,
you're already sanctified and you're יוצא yotzei at the same. Let me
first be in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and be sanctified and
then I'll be invalid once you take me out. So, okay, one
of the things you would need for this to work is not
just to be in the כלי שרת kli shares but it be
in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. But once
you bring it in, then you're stuck, then it'll become invalid overnight.
Okay, that's the גמרא's Gemara answer. חזקיה אמר, Chizkiyya amar, חזקיה Chizkiyya
says, כלי שרת אין מקדשין אלא מדעת. kli shares ein mekaddshin ela
midaas. No, actually you're wrong. Actually you can manipulate the situation so
it won't be sanctified. The vessels will not sanctify unless you want
them to. Okay, so if you specifically stipulate or maybe in a
סתם stam case, but if you specifically stipulate this should not be
sanctified when I fill it up in this barrel, it won't be
sanctified. So you're fine, you could use it the next morning. So
then why not use a non a sanctified barrel? Why does it
have to be a non-sanctified? Obviously the understanding is, you know, since
this is a temple ritual and, you know, it would be more
appropriate to use a sanctified barrel. So why not use one? Just
stipulate it shouldn't it shouldn't sanctify the water, you know, until the
next morning. So the גמרא Gemara says no, it's rabbinic, it's a
concern, גזירה שמא יאמרו לדעת נתקדשו. gezeira shema yomru l'daas niskadshu. People
won't know what's in your mind. People will think that you had
intent to sanctify and then they'll say look, they sanctified it, they
used a sanctified barrel, and they're going to then use the water
the next morning. So you see that even once something is sanctified
you can let it stay over till the next morning. That'll lead
to a lot of mistaken acts and mistaken understandings. Okay, so that's
his answer. אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, אמר רב ינאי אמר
רב זירא, amar Rav Yannai amar Rav Zeira, רב זירא Rav Zeira
in the name of רב
ינאי Rav Yannai in the name of רב זירא Rav Zeira so
it goes even further, אפילו תימא יש שיעור למים afillu teima yeish
shiur l'mayim וכלי שרת אין מקדשין מדעת. v'kli shares ein mekaddshin midaas.
Even if you say there's nothing to be worried about. Number one,
it won't sanctify without your intent. Number two, there's an exact amount
of the water, three לוג. Log. So the objective reality somebody looks
at it and will say, you know, forget the fact that they
don't know what's in your head. They'll say look, they should objectively
know that it can't sanctify, they'll see there's way too much water.
Nobody will think, oh, and obviously it already was sanctified. There's, you
know, ten gallons of water here. Nobody's going to think it's ready
yet. So therefore, what's the concern? Even there there's a concern. Why?
What's the concern? גזירה שמא יאמרו לקידוש ידים ורגלים מלאון. Gezeira shema
yomru l'kiddush yadayim v'raglayim mela'un.
People won't know why it was filled. People will say it was
filled for the כהן Kohen to wash his hands with the next
morning or the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol because, you know, the normal
כהן Kohen would wash it by the sink, there that would have
a well going a bucket going down into a well, but the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol they would have this more special thing they
would sometimes draw water for him to wash his hands. So there,
there is no minimum for water. So you might think there's nothing
to be concerned about, right? A, A,
you need intent, B, it's a huge amount of water and nobody
will think that it was the right amount for the ניסוך המים.
nisuch hamayim. You still don't want to do it because people won't
always have all the facts and people will think it was for
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and therefore they will they will think
look at that, the water was drawn, it was sanctified, and now
they used it the next morning. So that's a range of different
concerns about under what circumstances will the water be sanctified if it
is more and is what and you know and if you don't
have the intent for it to be so, you have the intent
for not to be so, and whether or not it's a clear
agreement is that if it's more than is what is needed it
won't work because the objective reality is not ready. But is there
really although we have a certain
amount
we
do If this water you drew the day before spilled or was
uncovered,
then you obviously can't use it, and you have to draw the
water from the well that's basically in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
even though it's not flowing water. נשפכה או נתגלתה, Nispacha o nitgalta,
so the גמרא Gemara is going to focus on the idea of
uncovered. What is the problem? As you might be aware in the
משניות, Mishnayot, there is, not here but elsewhere, there's a prevalent concern
of uncovered liquids that cannot be drunk. The גמרא Gemara explains that
it's based on a concern that snakes drank from it, let's take
a look at the, and there's poison in it, let's take a
look at what the גמרא Gemara says about this. דמאי, D'mai, says
the גמרא, Gemara, why is it? לאעבריה במסננת, Le'avrei bimsannenet, why not
just take this water that was uncovered and we can solve the
problem? Have it pass through a sieve and the sieve will take
out the poison. לימא מתניתין דלא כרבי נחמיה, Leima matnitin dela k'Rabbi
Nechemia, maybe our משנה Mishna is not like רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemia,
because there's a debate whether you can use a sieve to solve
the problems of uncovered liquids. דתניא, D'tanya, we've learned in a ברייתא,
Braita, מסננת, Mesannenet, you have a sieve that's over water, יש בו
משום גילוי, yesh bo mishum gilloie, the water is still considered to
be uncovered and it doesn't solve the problem. אמר רבי נחמיה, Amar
Rabbi Nechemia, said רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemia, אימתי, aimatai, when is that
true? בזמן שהתחתונה מגולה, bizman she'hatachtona megula, if the bottom thing where
the liquid is contained is uncovered, so even though there's a sieve
above, some snake could still have access to it from below. אבל
בזמן שהתחתונה מכוסה, Aval bizman she'hatachtona mechusa, if the bottom vessel, apparently
you would put, there'd be a top vessel which would contain the
liquid and then it would sort of like when you make like
filtered coffee, you know, there'd be something top which would hold it
and then it would slowly go down a sieve, so he says
into a bottom vessel, so he says if the bottom is covered
and the snake only had access to the top, it's no problem
because as it goes down the sieve the poison would get filtered
out.
A filter here. A filter.
A filter. Yeah.
Well, I don't think they had a filter with micro holes at
the time of the גמרא. Gemara.
But it was like a cloth.
You're right. Okay, so you're right, a sieve suggests larger holes, right?
Okay, so a filter's better. Okay, so it's a filter.
Okay, so אבל בזמן שהתחתונה מכוסה אף על פי שהעליונה מגולה, aval
bizman she'hatachtona mechusa af al pi she'haelyona megula, even though the top
one is uncovered, אין בו משום גילוי, ein bo mishum gilloie, there's
no problem. Why? מפני שארס נחש, mipnei she'eris nachash, because the poison
of a snake דומה לספוג, domeh lisvog, it's like a, it's like
a sponge, צף ועומד
במקומו, tzaf ve'omeid bimkomo, and it'll float at the top. So I
don't exactly get the sponge analogy other than that a sponge floats
on water, but anyway, it'll be filtered out by this filter. So
anyway, so according to רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemia, why what's the problem?
Just pass this water through a filter. So the גמרא Gemara says
no. אפילו תימא רבי נחמיה, Afilu teima Rabbi Nechemia, even according to
רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemia, it would be a problem, you couldn't use
this water. אימת אמר רבי נחמיה, Aimat amar Rabbi Nechemia, when does
רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia say that you can use the water? להדיוט,
le'hedyot, for a commoner. אבל לגבוה, aval l'gavoah, but for God, מי
אמר, mi amar, would he ever say such a thing? ולית ליה
לרבי נחמיה, V'leis lei l'Rabbi Nechemia, do you think רבי נחמיה Rabbi
Nechemia doesn't hold of the פסוק? pasuk? הקריבהו נא לפחתך, Hakrivehu na
lefachatecha, is this the type of thing you want to offer up
to your, you know, to your officer? הירצך, Hayirtzecha, like to a,
you know, a person in high position, הירצך, Hayirtzecha, will it find
favor in your, will it find favor for you? או הישא פניך,
O hayisa panecha, will it cause, you know, your lifting up of
your countenance? אמר ה' צבאות, Amar Hashem Tzevaot, says God, is this
the type of thing you want to bring to God? So even
if technically it's edible, we don't bring things on the מזבח mizbei'ach
that are not able to be eaten, but it's not the type
of thing that is acceptable on the מזבח, mizbei'ach, certainly not a
thing that we're doing for this whole major ritual, we're not going
to take something that was like, you know, that was in such
a lowly state. So therefore we don't want to offer it. Now
before we end, I want to make an interesting point, which is
two פרקים prokim ago, or whatever, the third פרק perek introduced לולב
ואתרוג, Lulav ve'Esrog, and you know, that opened also, you might remember,
with a positioning לולב lulav as a type of קרבן, korban, right?
You might remember the discussion of why is a stolen לולב lulav
invalid is because
it's מצוה הבאה בעבירה, mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah, very nice, but how does
the גמרא Gemara learn it? It learned it from a פסוק pasuk
that says והבאתם גזול ואת הפסח ואת החולה, ve'heveitem gazul ve'et hapisei'ach
ve'et hacholeh, is this the type of thing you want to bring
to God? Something stolen, something lame, something, you know, something sick. Okay,
and particularly sort of positions it as a קרבן, korban, here you
actually are dealing with something that's a קרבן, korban, that the water
that is brought, right? But basically you have לולב ואתרוג Lulav ve'Esrog
and then you have ערבות, Aravos, which had a whole מזבח mizbei'ach
ritual as well, right? And now you have the water, and it's
being bookended by two פסוקים psukim that in the opening of the
third פרק perek and the end of the fourth that are talking
about, you know, how do we present these types of things to
God? What is appropriate to be offering to God? Not only are
they on the same theme, guess what? They're both from מלאכי פרק
א'. Malachi Perek Aleph. And if you take a look at, what?
The הפטרה. Haftarah. Now the הפטרה, Haftarah, so did you recognize that
they were both from... To me, that was a big חידוש. chiddush.
So, okay. I said, "Oh wait a minute, those sound like the
exact same point, doesn't it? Like הירצך או הישא פניך Hayirtzekha o
hayissa panekha and the other one was הגישו פיסח וחולה?" haggishu piseach
v'choleh? Well actually it is the same point because they're both coming
from the exact, not just happened to be in the same פרק,
perek, but they're actually both coming—I mean that's exactly what that פרק
perek is saying. I mean, you know, God is sort of complaining
about the people
and how they have despised God's service, right? So it says like,
so here's the פסוק. pasuk.
ואם אדונים אני איה מוראי אמר ה' צבאות לכם הכהנים בוזי שמי
ואמרתם במה בזינו את שמך. מגישים על מזבחי לחם מגואל ואמרתם במה
גאלנוך. באמרכם שולחן ה' נבזה הוא. וכי תגישון עיור לזבוח אין רע
וכי תגישו פיסח וחולה אין רע. הקריבהו נא לפחתך הירצך או הישא
פניך אמר ה' צבאות.
V'im adonim ani aye morai amar Hashem tzevaot lachem hakohanim bozei shemi
v'amartem bameh bazinu et shemecha. Magishim al
mizbechi lechem m'go'al v'amartem bameh ge'al nucha. B'omrachem shulchan Hashem nivzeh hu.
V'chi tagishun iver lizboach ein ra v'chi tagishu piseach v'choleh ein ra.
Hakrivehu na l'pachatecha hayirtzecha o hayissa panecha amar Hashem tzevaot. So you
bring all of this stuff, פיסח, piseach, חולה, choleh, and you say
no big deal. Really? Is that the type of thing you want
to be bringing to God? And then it says, you know, and
then obviously the next פסוק, pasuk, not the next, but then it's
talking about ממזרח שמש ועד מבואו גדול שמי בגוים ובכל מקום מוקטר
מוגש לשמי מנחה טהורה כי גדול שמי בגוים אמר ה' צבאות. Mimizrach
shemesh v'ad mevo'o gadol shemi bagoyim uv'chol makom muktar mugash lishmi mincha
tehorah ki gadol shemi bagoyim amar Hashem tzevaot. Everybody is going to
be bringing, you know, my name is so great and look at
how you treat me. And then it says ואמרתם הנה מתלאה v'amartem
hineh matla'ah
whatever והבאתם גזול ואת הפיסח ואת החולה והבאתם את המנחה הארצה אותה
מידכם אמר ה'. v'havetem gazul v'et hapiseach v'et hacholeh v'havetem et hamincha
ha'ertzeh otah miyedchem amar Hashem. So etc. So it's really a little
bit in a whole פרשה parsha of קללה, klalah, so it doesn't
evoke necessarily positive associations when you realize the full context. But you
know, if this is ultimately, if סוכות Sukkot is us drawing close
to God and continuing this theme of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right?
And the לולב lulav and the ערבה aravah and all of this
is this sort of like, you know, this whole offering up even
outside of the מקדש Mikdash in a way, these rituals are, I
think it's very powerful, you know, the way it sort of pulls
together all of the, everything we've been learning in the third and
the fourth פרק perek and talking about what is this sort of
ideal way to be offering up to God and offering up our
best to God which is the theme of סוכות, Sukkot, right? You
have all of your success and all of the best and then
you put and then you appreciate that and you give thanks and
you rejoice before God. Yes.
I just want to add this idea of מים מגולים. mayim megulim.
Maybe it has more to do with being contaminated and sort of
being unsavory rather than dangerous. That's more of the aspect of being
unsavory. What do you mean? Well, would you really drink water that
filtered, that you thought filtered out the snake poison? I'm not so
sure, right?
Because you're afraid there's still a little bit of poison in it?
Yeah. Right. So you're, but the question you're saying is what makes
this inappropriate? Is what makes it inappropriate the possibility of still a
little poison or what makes it inappropriate is that it had to
go through a process of being filtered and that makes, right. I
think it's the latter, right?
If the poison is not an issue.
Exactly. So you're right, I agree with that. I think that that's
exactly the point. Like somebody, if you took water that was basically
waste water, I mean, I think some of our drinking water might
be this, but if we were more aware of it, you know,
water that really had all this disgusting stuff in it and somebody
promised, "Don't worry, we go through a whole process, 100% pure right
now," you would actually, you can believe them about that but it's
like, "Agh, I'm not going to drink that stuff." So anyway, Charlie
will tell us that that actually is what we probably drink.
Not waste water, but it's unfiltered.
Ah, well okay.
I was just wondering about the whole idea of מים מגולים mayim
megulim in general.
How much that is part of it. No, because that גמרא Gemara
really treats it like a strict איסור, issur, not just as something
like you know people wouldn't want to. But that's a separate פרשה
parsha in itself, the מים מגולים. mayim megulim. Okay, so הדרן עלך
לולב וערבה. Hadran alach Lulav v'Aravah. So that is the end of
that פרק. perek. And as I said, nice way of pulling together
the third and the fourth פרק, perek, and again, reinforcing a theme
that we've seen continuously reinforced the whole idea of מקדש Mikdash in
the context of סוכה Sukkah even though there are aspects that are
not in the מקדש. Mikdash. Okay, and now we turn, talking to
מקדש, Mikdash, the fifth פרק, perek, which is about the שמחת בית
השואבה. Simchat Beit Hashoeivah. And as I said, this is the party
that began the night before and ran through the entire night to
lead up to the drawing of the water that would take place
in the morning. Okay, so החליל חמישה ושישה. Hechalil chamishah v'shishah.
The playing of the, of the החליל, hechalil, which is the like
recorder, is that what we call it? Flute? Is five days and
six days. Meaning sometimes it will be five days, sometimes six. But
the musical instrument is really what that represents that were played for
the שמחת בית השואבה. Simchat Beit Hashoeivah. זה הוא החליל של בית
השואבה. Zeh hu hechalil shel Beit Hashoeivah.
This is the החליל hechalil that was played in the בית השואבה.
Beit Hashoeivah. שאינה דוחה לא את השבת ולא את יום טוב. She'eina
dochah lo et haShabbat v'lo et Yom Tov. You would not play
the music of the שמחת בית השואבה Simchat Beit Hashoeivah on שבת
Shabbat or on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
So therefore, what would that mean? You would draw water seven days,
the seven days of סוכות. Sukkot. The שמחת בית השואבה Simchat Beit
Hashoeivah would begin the night before. So the night of the first
night of יום טוב, Yom Tov, you would have maybe a שמחת
בית השואבה Simchat Beit Hashoeivah but you would not play the musical
instrument. Okay, so that's one day less, we're down to... If
שבת Shabbat? *Shabbos* was during the week, you would not do the
whole thing the night before on Friday night either. Not only that,
as we just learned, there wasn't even a ritual of drawing the
water outside of the מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash* and bringing it in on
שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* because of the carrying issue. So it would not
take place on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* and it would not take place
on יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*, so it could be either
five or six days you would have the music for the of
the שמחת בית השואבה Simchat Beit HaShoevah *Simchat Beis Hashoeva*. Let's take
a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, top of נ"א עמוד ב'
*Nun-Aleph Amud Bet*. אתמר *Itmar* was taught, רב יהודה בר אבינא *Rav
Yehuda bar Avina*, חד תני *chad tani* שואבה *Shoeva*, what גרסא *girsa*
is שואבה *Shoeva*, the drawing water of the water which makes a
lot of sense, that's what you would be doing as I said,
it would be a procession that would lead out, וחד תני *ve-chad
tani* חשובה *Chashuva*, which is interesting. שואבה חשובה *Shoeva Chashuva* shows about
an oral culture. If it was written you could never get that
mistake, right? But one version was חשובה *Chashuva*. The שמחת בית החשובה
*Simchas Beis HaChashuva*, which is funny because what's חשובה *Chashuva*? It's the
שמחה *Simcha*, probably שמחה חשובה *Simcha Chashuva*, so it probably not be
בית *Beis*, it would be שמחת בית החשובה *Simchat Bayit HaChashuva*, right?
As opposed to שמחת בית השואבה Simchat Beit HaShoeva. *Simchat Beis Hashoeva*,
this would probably be שמחת בית החשובה *Simchat Bayit HaChashuva*.
So וחד תני *ve-chad tani* חשובה *Chashuva*. אמר מר זוטרא *Amar Mar
Zutra*, מאן דתני *man de-tani* שואבה *Shoeva* לא Lo, משתבש *lo mishtabesh*,
ומאן דתני *u-man de-tani* חשובה *Chashuva* לא משתבש *lo mishtabesh*. Either one
is not necessarily, you know, this isn't corrupt and that isn't corrupt.
They're both good versions. מאן דתני *Man de-tani* שואבה *Shoeva* לא משתבש
*lo mishtabesh*, the one that's a שואבה *Shoeva* is not a corrupt
version, דכתיב *dikhtiv* ושאבתם מים בששון *u-shavtem mayim besasson*. Yeah, the whole
idea of joy in the drawing of the water, you know, that
obviously that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is going to be a major theme
throughout this discussion. That is means that that's why we do it
and that's the joy about this whole thing and that's about the
שואבה *Shoeva*, the drawing. ומאן דתני *U-man de-tani* חשובה *Chashuva* לא משתבש
*lo mishtabesh*, דאמר רב נחמן *d'amar Rav Nachman* מצוה חשובה היא *mitzvah
chashuva hi*, this is a very important מצוה *mitzvah*, ובאה מששת ימי
בראשית *ve-ba'ah misheshet yimei bereishit*, comes from the six days of creation.
So two interesting things to say. First of all, in terms of
the drawing, ושאבתם *u-shavtem*, a תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* quotes an
image or a metaphor, a symbolism rather,
that is, you know, I think very prevalent in thinking of שמחת
בית השואבה Simchat Beit HaShoeva *Simchas Beis Hashoeva* and he quotes it
from the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*. If you take a look at the תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot*, I'm really a mess today.
Sometimes you just have one of those mornings.
All right. I have to just hope it doesn't seep in. Save
my computer is the question. Thank you.
Computer is not קודש *Kodesh*.
Yeah, good point. So it won't sanctify the coffee that just spilled
on it. All right. Thank you. מקדש Mikdash שלא מדעת *mekadesh shelo
midaat*. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says חד תני *chad tani* שואבה *Shoeva*,
ירושלמי מפרש *Yerushalmi mefaresh*, שמשם שואבים רוח הקודש *shemisham shoavim Ruach HaKodesh*,
from there they draw the divine spirit, שהשכינה שורה מתוך שמחה *she-haShechina
shoreh mitoch simcha*, because the שכינה *Shechina* resides amongst joy, דכתיב *dikhtiv*
ויהי כנגן המנגן ותהי עליו רוח ה' *vayehi kenagen hamenagen vatehi alav
ruach Hashem* ומעשה דיונה *u-maaseh d'Yona* etc. so when יונה *Yona* went,
so it says that the symbolism of this is the drawing on
the divine presence and you know that sense of the overflow, the
שפע *shefa* and so on. Now that's very interesting also because you
know seeing it symbolically of course it is very important, the whole
idea of water, you know in an agricultural society obviously this is
key to their success and to their wellbeing. But you know it's
sometimes I get a little bit harder for us to relate, in
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* it's not so hard to relate, but it's
a little hard for us to relate about the whole sort of
water in the literal sense as that being the big thing. And
also what's the connection of שמחה *Simcha*? You know שמחה *Simcha* is
about the joy maybe of the previous year, but what's exactly the
שמחה *Simcha* of praying for water for the following year or symbolic
acts to show to beseech God for the water? Why is that
exactly שמחה *Simcha*? שמחה *Simcha* might be about the success of the
previous year. So thinking about the water symbolically is very powerful because
as we've been talking about the whole theme you know starting from
ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* but particularly יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, entering the
קודש קדשים *Kodesh Kodashim*, the סוכה *Sukkah*, ענני הכבוד *Anane Hakavod*, all
of this as we just mentioned the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash* theme, and
all of this sense about bringing in you know God's presence into
our lives for the following year like the drawing of the water
and the sense of the closeness to God leads to joy and
joy also brings about the closeness to God. So seeing this all
very symbolically about God's presence you know is very powerful and very
powerful in terms of tying into the theme of שמחה *Simcha*. So
that is in terms of just the שואבה *Shoeva* and the symbolism.
Now in terms of this ששת ימי בראשית *Sheishet Yimei Bereishit*, what
does that mean that this is a thing that... been around since
ששת ימי בראשית *sheishet yemei bereshit*. So if you take a look
at רש״י *Rashi*, רש״י *Rashi* says דאמרינן לעיל *damreinan l'eil* because we
said just yesterday שיתין נבראו מששת ימי בראשית *shittin nivre'u misheishet yemei
bereshit* לקבל הנסכים *lekabel hanesachim* that the caverns were created underground for
the purpose of the water. Now that's a little for the purpose
of the libation. Now that's a little funny because first of all,
as you remember, there was a debate whether they were, there were
underground caverns, even if there were, whether they were man-made or naturally
made, God-made, number one. Number two is also
that mostly it was for the wine, right? Those caverns, the libations
that went into them were wine libations. It was only one week
it was the water libation. So I don't know, everyday ever שמחת
בית השואבה Simchat Beit HaShoeivah *simchas beis hashoeva* because of the caverns
and the wine? So it's a little funny exactly connecting it to
that. What I would suggest, not necessarily that it contradicts רש״י *Rashi*,
in addition to רש״י *Rashi*, but whatever, what I would suggest is
the other idea that if you have, look, it says how many
days would you have it? Number one, let's just point that out.
You do the libation seven days, but how many days would you
have the שמחת בית השואבה *simchas beis hashoeva*? Six, five or six,
but let's say six would be the max. Well, you have six
in ששת ימי בראשית *sheishet yemei bereshit* first of all, and if
you think about water, right, way at the beginning of the מסכת
*masechet*, one of the earliest learning
derivations of the idea of סכך *s'chach* was that סכך *s'chach* represents
ענני כבוד *ananei kavod*, but then it learns from the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* of ואד יעלה מן הארץ והשקה *v'eid ya'aleh min ha'aretz v'hishka*,
את כל *et kol*, you know, את כל *et kol*, what's the
פסוק *pasuk*? ואד יעלה מן הארץ והשקה את כל פני האדמה *v'eid
ya'aleh min ha'aretz v'hishka es kol pnei ha'adamah*.
So about the cloud, which is ענני כבוד *ananei kavod*, but not
learning from the ענני כבוד *ananei kavod* of the מדבר *midbar*, learning
from the original cloud that rose up in the story of בריאה
*beriah*, creation, and gave water to the world. So if you think
about it, I would suggest that what this is evoking is the
whole creation motif and water, obviously, I mean God, water starts right
in the beginning of creation, right, because of תהו ובהו *tohu vavohu*,
you know, ארץ ומים *eretz umayim* and all of that. And the
water motif here, and of course this is also בריאת העולם *berias
ha'olam* is this period of the year and the beginning of a
new cycle and that sort of like a joy in terms of,
obviously there's a, that brings us back to the water. There's a
בקשה *bakasha* element for the water, but there's also a joy in
the nature and in the world and in the natural world and
in all of this that God has given us. So I would
suggest that that is the, you know, that it was already, that
it's חשובה מששת ימי בראשית *chashuva misheishet yemei bereshit* pulling up that
other theme of what's going on here with the whole focus on
water.
Okay, so let's see now as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. תנו
רבנן החליל דוחה את השבת *Tanu rabanan hachalil docheh es haShabbos*. The
החליל *hachalil*, the flute overrides שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*, דברי רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה Rabbi Yose be'Rabbi Yehuda *divrei Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda*, the words
of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose be'Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi
Yehuda*. וחכמים אומרים *Vachachamim omrim*, and the sages say, אף יום טוב
Yom Tov, אינו דוחה *af Yom Tov eino docheh*, not only does
it not override שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*, it doesn't override יום טוב Yom
Tov *Yom Tov*, which it seems to be our משנה Mishnah *mishnah*.
אמר רב יוסף מחלוקת בשיר של קרבן Amar Rav Yosef: Machloket b'shir
shel korban, *Amar Rav Yosef machlokes b'shir shel korban*. רב יוסף Rav
Yosef *Rav Yosef* says, one minute, let's be clear here. Nobody thinks
that the party, the שמחת בית השואבה *simchas beis hashoeva*, the musical
instruments for that would override שבת Shabbat? *Shabbos*. The issue that it
might, musical instruments might override שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos* is the song that
they sang to accompany the bringing of sacrifices. So basically here's the
rule that with, you know, with every, with all of, first of
all in general, because as we talked about the נסכים *nesachim* before,
with all sacrifices that were not sin related, not חטאת *chatas* and
not אשם *asham*, you would bring נסכים *nesachim*, okay? You would bring
wine libations. But by the sacrifices that were communal obligatory sacrifices, which
basically would be the morning sacrifices and the morning and the afternoon,
the תמיד *tamid* and the מוספין *musafin* on the day that you
have a מוסף musaf. *musaf*, so with communal obligatory sacrifices at the
time of the pouring of the נסכים *nesachim*, you would have the
שיר shir *shir* that the לויים Levi'im *Levi'im* would say. Now it
would only be done during the pouring of the wine, because this
is actually interesting because it has implications in other areas of הלכה
*halacha*, אין שירה shira אלא על היין *ein shira ela al hayayin*.
So an idea that song is over wine, which is basically why
the basis of why we have rituals that are done over wine,
like saying קידוש *Kiddush* over wine and הבדלה *Havdalah* over wine. That
idea by the way of wine as giving significance to it and
as ritualizing it is very important because most of the rituals we
do over wine, the regular ones, are in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
קידוש *Kiddush* and הבדלה *Havdalah*. But most of the other ones that
we do or all the other ones that we do are not
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* but were adopted soon afterwards at the
גאוני *Geonic* period because of how they give sort of weight and
ritual significance. So the fact you use wine at a ברית מילה
*bris milah*, the fact you use wine at a wedding, all of
this is not in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. All of the two
cups of wine, אירוסין *eirusin* and נישואין *nisu'in*, all of that is
post-גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has it as קידוש *Kiddush*, הבדלה
*Havdalah*, or ברכת המזון *birchas hamazon* depending on if you think you
need it for ברכת המזון *birchas hamazon*. Okay, anyway, that's שיר shir
על היין *shir al hayayin*. So when they did the wine libations
during the communal obligatory sacrifices, there would be the song of the
לויים Levi'im *Levi'im*. השיר שהלויים היו אומרים *Hashir shehaLevi'im hayu omrim*, like
which we say every morning, which would be done at the תמיד
*tamid*, תמיד של שחר tamid shel shachar, *tamid shel shachar* and תמיד
של בין הערביים tamid shel bein ha'arbaim *tamid shel bein ha'arbayim*. Although
we only say the שחרית *shacharis*, it was done at both of
them. Okay, so that's the שיר *shir*. Now With that שיר, you
would have some of the לווים Leviim singing and you would have
some of them playing musical instruments. So here, would they play the
musical instruments on שבת? Shabbat. That's the question. So what so what
who is saying who is it that is saying this? I'm sorry.
יוסי
ברבי יהודה
Yosi b'Rebbi
Yehuda
is saying no, not יוסי ברבי יהודה, Yosi b'Rebbi Yehuda, רב יוסף
Rav Yosef is saying is that this discussion of do you play
the musical instruments on שבת Shabbat, is not a discussion about the
party that you'd have on סוכות. Sukkot. That would not be musical
instruments on שבת Shabbat or יום טוב. Yom Tov The issue is
the real song, you know, song and music that would accompany קרבנות.
korbanot. That is the, you know, that's like the real קרבן korban
related, directly קרבן korban related, and there the question is would that
override be done even on שבת. Shabbat, So let's let's just read
this. עיקר שירה בכלי וביפה... Ikar shira bikli u-vif-eh... so how does
that map on? אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef, מחלוקת בשיר של
קרבן, korban. the song that accompanies the קרבן. korban רב יוסף סבר,
Rav Yosef savar, רב יוסף Rav Yosef is of the opinion, עיקר
שירה בכלי, Ikar shira bikli, the fundamental שירה shira is with a
musical instrument. Meaning, when the תורה Torah says when the תורה Torah
doesn't say it explicitly, when there's an idea that a קרבן korban,
has to be accompanied with song, does it mean words song or
does it mean with music? So that's the debate. רב יוסף says
the primary thing is the music. ועבודה היא Va-avodah hi and therefore
it's an עבודה avodah in the מקדש, Mikdash, although it's not a
full עבודה avodah because the לווים Leviim are doing it, but okay,
ודוחה את השבת, v'docheh et haShabbat, but that would justify it overriding
שבת. Shabbat So can you play the musical instruments when you do
the שירה that you normally do with קרבנות korbanot at the time
of the קרבן, korban can you do it on שבת? Shabbat If
the music is central, yes. רבנן סברי עיקר שירה בפה. Rabanan savri:
Ikar shira b'peh. The music is just an accompaniment. That's not central.
What's central is the song, what's said in the mouth, the oral
song. לאו עבודה היא Lav avodah hi and the music is not
really central to the עבודה avodah and therefore ואינה דוחה את השבת,
v'einah docha et haShabbat, cannot be done on שבת. Shabbat. אבל שיר
של שמחת בית השואבה, Aval shir shel Simchat Beit HaShoevah, but the
whole music and singing that was done around the שמחת בית השואבה
from the night before, not talking about the thing that accompanied the
bringing of a קרבן korban, at the moment of the bringing of
a קרבן, korban. that דברי הכל שמחה היא, divrei hakol Simcha hi,
it's just joy, it's not an עבודה, avodah, it's not it's a
joy that accompanies, you know, or that's done whatever to build up
to an עבודה avodah but is not part of the עבודה. avodah.
Okay, שמחה היא ואינה דוחה את השבת, Simcha hi v'einah docha et
haShabbat, cannot override שבת. Shabbat So our משנה that says it was
not done on שבת, Shabbat. not done on יום טוב, is what
everybody would agree. The only one that would suggest that it's done
on שבת Shabbat. and יום טוב would be that that is done
at the time of the קרבן. korban, I want to say two
things about that. One is, first of all, it's it, you know,
suggestive to associate the idea of the שיר by the קרבנות korbanot
with the idea in the תורה Torah that has something like that,
which is the חצוצרות, chatzotzrot, the trumpets, right? Except the חצוצרות chatzotzrot
are the תורה Torah says
וביום שמחתכם ובמועדיכם ובראשי חדשיכם ותקעתם בחצצרת, u-v'yom simchatchem u-v'moadeichem u-v'roshei chodsheichem
u-tkatem bachatzotzrot, not every day. The שיר was done every day, the
תמיד של שחר, תמיד של בין הערביים and also the מוסף. But
that so it's not the same and actually when there is יום
טוב and ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh you would also have the חצוצרות.
chatzotzrot. But because the חצוצרות chatzotzrot are in the תורה, Torah, they
are, and first of all who, you
know, משה Moshe made the well whatever, forget that, because the חצוצרות
chatzotzrot are in the תורה Torah they are real עבודה, avodah, and
guess who plays the חצוצרות? chatzotzrot? Any guesses?
No, it's a real עבודה avodah so it's done only by the
כהנים. kohanim. Only the כהנים kohanim can do the חצוצרות. chatzotzrot. But
not only by the way can the music that's done for the
לווים Leviim be be, what do you call it, be done by
לווים Leviim and not כהנים, kohanim, which shows that even when the
גמרא says it's an עבודה avodah it does not mean the full
sense of עבודה, avodah, but the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens עיקר שירה
בפה, Ikar shira b'peh, that the music is just an accompaniment and
therefore the actual central thing of part of the עבודה avodah is
the song. And guess what? Because the music is an accompaniment, you
know who else could do the music? Not just לווים, Leviim, even
ישראלים Yisraelim could do the music. So it's quite fascinating that, you
know, we sort of it's important to get those ideas straight. The
חצוצרות chatzotzrot which is in the תורה Torah only the כהנים, kohanim,
this idea that the עבודה avodah is actually the idea that it's
an עבודה avodah is it's one of the עבודות avodot of the
לווים. Leviim. That's actually where the place the גמרא learns it from.
The לווים Leviim are said, you know, עבודת מתנה, avodat matnah, what
is
it, עבודת מתנה? avodat matnah? But anyway, one of the פסוקים pesukim
of עבודה avodah by the לווים, Leviim, the גמרא says oh that
means what is the עבודה avodah of the לווים? Leviim? At in
the תורה Torah it was carrying, you know, the משכן, Mishkan, but
post the תורה Torah what was it? So the גמרא says the
לווים Leviim primarily have two עבודות. avodot. They watch the gates of
the מקדש Mikdash. and they do the song. Okay, so it's an
עבודה avodah but it's an עבודה avodah of the לווים. Leviim. And
which is the עבודה, avodah, right? It is either the song... ing
or the musical instruments and that's what's being debated here. Okay, so
here you get this question, right, is it the singing, is it
the musical instruments? And that's where it would determine whether the music
would override שבת, Shabbat but that's only the music being played with
the קרבן, korban not the שמחת בית השואבה. One other important point,
which is what is the big deal here? Playing music on שבת
Shabbat is, right, just a rabbinic concern. Right, maybe you'll come to
fix it, whatever the issue is. What do you mean override שבת
Shabbat, and Torah? And תוספות actually struggles with this because תוספות says
other גמרות Gemaras make it seem like it's a complete non-issue playing
the music instruments on שבת. Shabbat. Like whether עיקר שירה בפה, ikar
shira b'peh, עיקר שירה בכלי, ikar shira b'kli, the whole thing is
a rabbinic thing, big deal. We normally say אין שבות במקדש. ein
shvut b'Mikdash. We don't worry about rabbinic issues about שבת in the
מקדש Mikdash, when it relates to the קרבנות. korbanot. So what's the
big deal, you know? And therefore maybe you could say the opposite.
Maybe you could say no, actually, they're debating maybe even שמחת בית
השואבה you should be allowed to do it on שבת. Again, if
all it is is the rabbinic concerns. So it is interesting that
the גמרא sort of heightens the concern around the playing of the
music and says that it would even be a debate about it
even at the time of the bringing of the קרבן korban. where
תוספות says from other גמרות Gemaras it's like a non-issue, of course
you would do it. Okay, Dov, you had a question. Dov L.,
yes. No? Okay. So now the גמרא continues. Okay. אמר רב יוסף,
Amar Rav Yosef.
says אמר רב יוסף. מנא אמינא לה, Mina amina lah, where do
I get this from? דהא פליגי, de'hapaligi, that this is what they
debate about, that they debate the music instruments that would accompany the
pouring of the wine of the קרבן. דתניא, detanya, we taught in
a ברייתא: Baraita: כלי שרת שעשה אנשי של עץ, kli sharet she'asah
anshei shel etz, if you have holy vessels in the מקדש, right,
the service vessels technically, but whatever, we just referred to this before,
the sanctified vessels that you want to use in the various עבודות
avodot in the מקדש. What if they're made out of wood? Normally
obviously they're made out of silver and gold. What if they were
made out of wood? רבי פוסל ורבי יוסי ברבי יהודה מכשיר. Rabbi
posel v'Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda machshir. Rabbi invalidates and Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Yehuda says it's kosher.
Now you might notice it's the same Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda here
who says kosher, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda before said
that the music overrides שבת. Okay, so he's going to try to
connect these two Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehudas. The music overrides שבת with
that a כלי שרת kli sharet can be made out of wood.
What's the connection? So let's take a look. So he
says, מאן דמכשיר, man de'machshir, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda who says you
can have one of the כלי שרת kli sharet out of wood,
סבר עיקר שירה בכלי. savar ikar shira b'kli. He says
look, when the לויים Levi'im played the musical instruments, that is the
key, the key, the central עבודה avodah of the לויים Levi'im is
the playing of the musical instruments, not the singing. Okay, so big
deal. ויליפינן מאבובא דמשה. ve'yalfinan me'avuva de'Moshe. Well, let me tell you,
how many musical instruments have you seen that are made out of
metal? Okay, what would the musical instruments be made out of? If
you've got a flute, what do you think it's made out of?
Wood or reed or something like that, right? There's metal flutes. All
right, but anyway, not as presumably not the ones they would use.
Are they? Okay, fine. I was making a point, I didn't mean
non-existent. But the assumption is that they would have a flute, the
primary flute, other גמרות Gemaras say it would be wood, you can't
even coat them with metal. So he says well, if you think
that that's the real עבודה avodah of the לויים Levi'im is the
music instrument, then that's a כלי שרת kli sharet made out of
wood. Okay, and therefore that should teach you that כלי שרת kli
sharet can be made out of wood. And that links with Rabbi
Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda before that said that you can do it on
שבת because he thinks the music is the עיקר. ikar. ומאן דפסל,
u'man de'pasel, and Rabbi who invalidates, סבר עיקר שירה בפה. savar ikar
shira b'peh. No, the עבודה avodah of the לויים was, their primary
shira was the song. And therefore the music instruments were not עיקר
ikar to the עבודת לויים avodat Levi'im as I said before, even
non-לויים could do it according to this idea, and therefore they weren't
a כלי שרת. kli sharet. דלא ילפינן מאבובא דמשה, delo yalfinan me'avuva
de'Moshe, and we don't learn out from Moshe, again, Moshe goes and
stands, goes way back, you know? From, and we don't learn from
Moshe's flute. So here's what he's saying is I got a great
explanation and it maps onto this other debate of Rabbi and Rabbi
Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda, which is the debate about can you have wood
כלי שרת. kli sharet. Everybody will assume that we had wood musical
instruments, were they כלי שרת kli sharet or not? That depends whether
עיקר שירה בפה ikar shira b'peh or עיקר שירה בכלי. ikar shira
b'kli. Ah, so look at this. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda who says
that it was a music who I understand is saying that we
can say that the music. Yes. I'm not an expert in חומש
Chumash like when did משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu play the flute? Yeah,
I didn't explain that phrase. I didn't explain, there you go, I
didn't, maybe... he was like herding the sheep in the מדרש? Midrash?
That's what I... is that a מדרש? Midrash? No. Well, I don't
know. All רש"י Rashi says, I didn't explain. It's a beautiful image
but we just... yeah, right, that's true. Well we also had, don't
forget, we had two פרקים prakim before, אשירה דמשה. Ashira deMoshe. So
maybe from, we took from משה's Moshe אשירה ashira we took some
wood. My point being that it doesn't mean that literally it was
his. It means like biblical, going way back. That's at least the
way רש"י Rashi explains it. Okay, רש"י's Rashi what? In used during
his time. Right, used during his time. The clear meaning, I'll try
to find what is in רש"י. Rashi. In used, in used the
type of חליל chalil prevalent in his time? רש"י Rashi says, ואבוב
היה במקדש מימות משה. ve'avuv haya baMikdash miymot Moshe. Okay? So same
way we talk about like אשירה דמשה. Ashira deMoshe. Yeah, but it
is a nice image. But that says that משה Moshe would play
a flute? That there was one flute from the days of משה
Moshe that was made from a reed that was made in the
Temple and then they wanted to plate it with gold. All right,
wait, right, right. Where? Okay, very nice. Yeah. All right, so let's
continue. So that's what he says, like a great פשט. pshat. And
it's all about this question of, is עיקר שירה בפה ikar shira
b'peh or עיקר שירה בכלי? ikar shira b'kli? And therefore they're not
debating שמחת בית השואבה on שבת, they're debating the general musical instruments
that would come with the קרבנות korbanot on שבת. So the גמרא
says like this: לא, that's not necessarily the debate, דכולי עלמא עיקר
שירה, d'kulei alma ikar shira, עיקר שירה בכלי. ikar shira b'kli. Everybody
could say that the music, that it is the primary עבודת הלויים
avodat haLevi'im is the music and therefore we do have wooden כלי
שרת klei shareit in the musical instruments. So what's the debate? דהכא
בדנין אפשר משאי אפשר קמיפלגי. Dehacha b'danin efshar mish'ee efshar kamiflagi. Here
the debate is whether you learn out of something that has possible
alternatives from something that did not have possible alternatives. Meaning the reason
the
musical instruments were made out of wood was because they needed to
be, they needed to be made out of wood to create the
type of music that they wanted to create. Okay, so there we
would allow it to be out of wood. But any other vessel
could be made out of
metal. That's אפשר. efshar. So the case of the music was אי
אפשר. ee efshar. You had no alternative. So you were allowed to
do it out of wood. That doesn't mean in the case where
you have alternatives that we can use that as a precedent. Okay?
So believe me, as a
dean I always, I know how students like to look at any
situation as a precedent for what they want to do even though
that situation had special circumstances. That's the debate here, דנין אפשר משאי
אפשר. danin efshar mish'ee efshar.
Yeah, that comes up, yeah, very much this question, yeah, frequently. מאן
דמכשר סבר, Man d'machshir savar, the one that says you can use
wooden vessels holds, דנין אפשר משאי אפשר. danin efshar mish'ee efshar. You
can apply a case that's, that has no
alternative and say, but nevertheless we're going to make a precedent out
of it. It tells you a principle. The principle is you can
learn out, you can have wooden כלי שרת. klei shareit. So even
you can learn a case that has possible alternatives from one that
had no alternatives. ומאן דפסיל סבר, U'man d'pasil savar, and the one
that invalidates says, לא דנין אפשר משאי אפשר. lo danin efshar mish'ee
efshar. You can't learn out cases where you have alternatives from cases
you didn't have alternatives. It does not set a precedent; it does
not set a rule. Okay, so that's one possibility. ואי בעית אימא,
V'ee ba'it eima, if you want I'll tell you, דכולי עלמא דעיקר
שירה בפה d'kulei alma d'ikar shira b'peh ואין דנין אפשר משאי אפשר.
v'ein danin efshar mish'ee efshar. Everybody could hold that basically the עבודת
הלויים avodat haLevi'im was the music and you did have wooden כלי
שרת. klei shareit. But you know what? That's irrelevant. Everybody could also
agree you cannot learn out cases of possible alternatives from ones of
no possible alternatives. Everybody agrees that the fact that they used wooden
musical instruments and will acknowledge that they were כלי שרת klei shareit
is completely irrelevant to the question about the other כלי שרת. klei
shareit. Okay, so then what's the debate about can כלי שרת klei
shareit be of wood or not? דהכא, Dehacha, here the issue is
במילף מנורה בכללי ופרטי או בריבוי ומיעוט. b'milyaf menora b'klali u'prati o
b'ribui u'mi'ut. What can we learn from the מנורה? Menorah? The מנורה
Menorah is also being treated here not as just furniture as part
of the building. It's a type of a כלי שרת. klei shareit.
It's the כלי kli that you use to do the act of
הדלקה. hadlaka. And again it's a little funny because you wouldn't think
it's the same as this type of movable stuff, it has a
fixed place. But okay, it's a...
and the question is that was made out of metal. Can you,
what but what the תורה Torah tells you about all the types
of vessels that were made, basically were metal or coated with metal
at least. So what can you learn from the מנורה Menorah as
a paradigm for other כלי שרת? klei shareit? You could say... what
you learn is that it all has to be out of gold.
But what alternatives did you have by the מנורה? Menorah? What בדיעבד
Bidiavad could you make the מנורה Menorah out of? Some people might
be familiar with the story, it is even in the book of
Maccabees if memory serves, that when they entered in the- the Hasmoneans
entered into the מקדש,
they used their spears, I think it's in the book of Maccabees,
maybe they used their spears to be, you know, their iron spears
to make an ad hoc מנורה. Menorah. So it doesn't have to
be בדיעבד Bidiavad out of gold. What alternatives do you have by
a מנורה Menorah will tell me what are my range of possible
כלי שרת. Klei Shareit. How do you learn it out depends on
your hermeneutics. There are two hermeneutics. כלל ופרט Klal u'Prat or ריבוי
ומיעוט. Ribuy u'Miyut.
The basic way that
these rule out- and I'll give you the example by the מנורה,
Menorah, might as well, because that's the exact example we're going to
look at, okay, which is ועשית מנורת
זהב
טהור,
Ve'asita Menorat
Zahav
Tahor, so that's just gold, okay, right? מקשה
תיעשה המנורה,
Miksha Tei'aseh
HaMenorah, which sort of doesn't give you any limit. So that's considered
to be a more general statement. Okay, so that's general and this
is specific.
And we're going to also say that I think the verse says
ועשית. Ve'asita.
Where- what- where's the first general?
ועשית מנורת. Ve'asita Menorat. Okay, it's very- it's very like not clear
how we can always claim that some things are general, you know,
statements, but okay. So we say general, specific, general. By the way,
so a better פסוק for this, I'm going to use this as
an example because of what we're talking about, but a better פסוק
for this is
by פרשת מצוה מעשר שני, Parshat Mitzva Ma'aser Sheni, where it says
ונתת הכסף. Venatata HaKesef. Here's a real כלל. klal. ונתת הכסף בכל
אשר
תאווה נפשך.
Venatata HaKesef Bechol Asher Te'aveh
Nafshecha.
Anything you want! בבקר ובצאן וביין ובשכר. Bevakar Uve'tzon Uvayayin Uvashachar. Okay?
ובכל אשר תשאלך
נפשך. Uvechol Asher Tish'alecha Nafshecha.
So anything you want, right? Oh, but I mention all those things
in the middle. So what does that tell me? Really anything? Can
I buy a house with it? Can I buy a suit of
clothes? No. I said ביין ובשכר בבקר ובצאן. Bevayin Uvashachar Bevakar Uve'tzon.
I don't mean anything, I mean things like that. So that's the
problem of when you say a general and then a specific, what
are you really saying? Okay? I'll give you the example, say, you
know, what do you want for dinner? You can make me anything-
steak. So what did I really say? Hey, really anything? Or, you
know, okay, how about if it was a hamburger? Okay, that's good
too. How much is it really just the last thing, or the
fact that I started by saying anything? So that is the question.
And there are two basic different approaches to the hermeneutics you use
here. Okay, כלל ופרט Klal u'Prat says that כלל ופרט- Klal u'Prat
פרט prat means we are being specific. We are being specific. So
that means that even if you open with a general statement, by
the time you get to being specific, that's really what I mean.
I really mean that this is the explanation. When I say anything,
I don't mean anything. When I say anything you want, what I
really mean is the list that follows. Okay, so the- that's what
you get at that statement. That's אין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט. Ein
Baklal Ella Mah Shebaprat. Okay, there you're limited to the פרט. prat.
And then what I never understood was why do you need- when
you don't need the כלל, klal, but what you need the כלל
klal for is when you get the next כלל. klal. When then
it says ובכל אשר תשאלך נפשך. Uvechol Asher Tish'alecha Nafshecha.
Because then when you get another כלל, klal, let's say I say,
what do you- what do you want for dinner? Make me anything,
a steak, really anything. Okay, so now- so okay, we decided we're
going to have salad with salmon. I don't care what I said!
But we're going to have it instead- we're not going to have
steak, we'll have like I don't know, hamburgers or something. All right,
that's also good. So when you get to a general, even though
you're saying anything here and anything here, what you really mean is
anything like the thing in the middle. So כלל ופרט וכלל, Klal
Prat u'Klal, it becomes anything like the פרט. prat. Okay? So that
is that principle of כלל ופרט klal u'prat as
a paradigm for what you... exactly.
Now as opposed to- that's one way of doing it. As opposed
to one that answers the question Dov is asking, which is, this-
okay, I sort of get it, but when you're just at this
כלל ופרט klal u'prat stage, you don't understand why you needed to
open with a general statement. So the other principle is called ריבוי
ומיעוט. Ribuy u'Miyut. Okay, which means it's- the word here is not-
is limiting, it's not פרט, prat, it's not specific, but it's limiting.
ריבוי Ribuy is generalizing, this is limiting. So this basically at stage
one gets to where this got to at stage two. This says
when you say anything, a steak, I'm already there because you opened
by saying anything, you mean anything like the thing I'm about to
say. So this already says like the- you know, like the specifics.
That's what מיעוט miyut means. It's limiting, but it's not being specific.
It's not saying exactly this. It's more limiting. by giving examples but
it really already means anything like the specifics. So what happens when
you get another ריבוי? ribbuy? So what and then afterwards you said
and really it could be anything, so the combination here means that
it's anything except what is completely different. Except what is completely different.
So according to this, right, in my lovely example, if I said,
you know, a steak, you know, anything, a steak, really anything is
fine. So okay, hamburgers is okay, chicken is okay, but if we're
just having like salad and tofu, like no, that's not okay. That's
the ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי. ribbuy u'miut u'ribbuy. You can really be already
here you were talking about anything similar to the example, and at
this stage it has the only thing you're excluding is something that's
considered to be completely different. So let's take a look now how
that plays out in terms of the מנורה. menorah. So it says
like this. Oh yes, this, right? Yeah, so it's for we have
two minutes. Okay. So במאי דמנורה בכללי ופרטי או בריבוי ומיעוט קמיפלגי.
bemai de'menorah bikhlali u'perati o biribbuy u'miut kamiflagi. רבי Rebbi darshes כללי
ופרטי. klali u'perati. רבי Rebbi does the כלל klal and פרט prat
approach. רבי Rebbi יוסי ברבי יהודה darshes ריבוי ומיעוטא, ribbuy u'miuta, the
ריבוי ribbuy and the מיעוט. miut. רבי darshes כללי ופרטי. klali u'perati.
ועשית מנורת, ve'asita menorat, כלל, klal, which is a פשט. pshat. זהב
טהור, zahav tahor, פרט, prat, so general, specific. מקשה תיעשה המנורה, mikshah
te'aseh hamenorah, חזר וכלל, chazar ve'khallal, so then it's making it general.
כלל ופרט וכלל, klal u'prat u'khlal, what do you do when you
get that trio? אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט, ei attah dan
ella ke'ein haprat, by that principle, all you're at is stage two.
It has to be similar to the specific example. So what's similar
to gold? מה הפרט מפורש של מתכת, mah haprat meforash shel matechet,
it's a metal. אף כל של מתכת, af kol shel matechet, metal,
that's all you get. It has to be metal because you have
to be similar to the specific of gold. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
darshes ריבוי ומיעוט. ribbuy u'miut. He does the other hermeneutic, not specific
but limiting. ועשית מנורת, ve'asita menorat, ריבה, ribbah, that's the general. זהב
טהור, zahav tahor, מיעט, mi'et, that's limiting. So already at first for
him you're already saying anything like gold. For him you're already at
the idea of metal by stage one. And then it says מקשה
תיעשה המנורה, mikshah te'aseh hamenorah, beat it and you should make the
מנורה menorah without any specific, חזר וריבה, chazar ve'ribbah, now it's more
general. ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי, ribbuy u'miut u'ribbuy, so you have general, limiting,
and general. ריבה הכל, ribbah hakkol, so the last one is pretty
much including anything. So מאי רבי? mai rabbi? What's it including? רבי
כל מילי, rabbi kol milli, it's including anything. מאי מיעט? mai mi'et?
The only thing that it's excluding is something completely different. מיעט של
חרס, mi'et shel cheres, you can't make it out of pottery. But
wood, right? Like that you can't make it, and therefore according to
this, because of a different hermeneutics, he would say you can use
כלי שרת, kli sharet, but it
has nothing to do with the question whether עיקר שירה בפה ikar
shira be'peh or עיקר שירה בכלי. ikar shira bi'khli. Okay.